Arseniy Shchepetnov

Lead Data Scientist

Address: Saint-Petersburg, Russian Federation

Email: a.shchepetnov@gmail.com

Phone: +79531494268 GitHub: ArseniyShchepetnov LinkedIn: Arseniy Shchepetnov Medium: Arseniy Shchepetnov

Objective

Data Science/Lead Data Science, Development

Relevant skills

My interest vector is referred to Data Science, Research and Development, Product Development related to technologies. As for my experience I have:

- 5 years of Data Science and Algorithmic Research
- 2+ years of people managment
- 8 years of practical development in different languages
- 5 years of academic research in Theoretical Physics (Quantum Physics)

In different organizations I gained experience in Digital Signal Processing, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, etc, and I have developed many product components and algorithmic solutions for business value, that were successfully deployed. Under my direction as Data Science Team Leader a new data processing service was developed for the analysis of geological data using deep learning models, where I have designed full infrastructure from processing raw data piplines to DL/ML processing and model library. Also, I have developed FastAPI service on parallel project.

I have advanced development skills with Python including linting, CI/CD, FastAPI, Flask and others (see examples on GitHub), ability to create interactive visualisation tools and dashboards. Other languages that are covered with my experience are C++, Fortran, R.

Academic research in physics provided a fundamental pillar and a useful tool for my development in Data Science.

For personal NLP project I have developed web scraping tool (ScraPy + MongoDB) and deployed it on Google Colab. It produced database with 10k processed articles with summary in one day.

Employment history

May 2021 — Now **Lead Data Scientist/Team Lead/Senior Consultant -> Manager** «PWC» (Technology, Artificial Intelligence), Saint-Petersburg

I am leading and developing multiple Data Science projects related to Bayesian Networks, Deep Learning and Machine Learning. Data Science format includes both algorithmic and software development.

- Developed MLOps architecture and code for Deep Learning models for well logs data analysis.
- Designed and developed software for Bayesian Networks using FastAPI plus serious optimizations of python library for Bayesian Networks.
- Well Logs retrieval research with Deep Learning models was done under my direction, the client was satisfied and results were used in geology.
- I hired 2 junior and 1 intern Data Scientists and in less than a year got 2 junior and 1 middle.
- Due to good performance I was promoted up to the Manager Grade.
- I holded a speech on careers days in two universities.

After rebranding in July the unit is called «Digital Formula of Trust».

May 2018 — May 2021

Data Scientist/Lead Data Scientist/Team Lead

«IBM STC» (GBS, "Cognitive Practice Team"), Saint-Petersburg, Moscow

Consulting services in the area of Data Science and Artificial Intellegence. Research and development of Data Science and Al solutions for clients.

- Developed models for searching oil intervals with Deep Learning and Machine Learning models. Real oil was extracted in locations that models predicted.
- I carried out research on correlation of wells for spatial analysis and designed several models. Predictions were used by the client.
- Using bokeh package I have developed interactive dashboards for geological data, including GIS signals and layers vizualizations and maps.
- I developed model serving solutions for research optimization.
- I grew from middle to senior Data Scientist and started leading a team.

Aug 2016 — **Research and Development**May 2018 — «Healbe corp.», Saint-Petersburg

Research and Development of algorithms for the wearable device sensors.

- I developed algorithms for custom piezoelectric and optical devices which were successfully deployed.
- I developed several utilities for data transfer from wearable devices and applying algorithms on the local machine which were used also in parallel projects.

Nov 2013 — **Engineer-programmer**Feb 2016 «Russian Institute for Pow

«Russian Institute for Power Radiobuilding», Saint-Petersburg

• I developed PostgreSQL database and UI on C++/Qt4 which was successfully deployed for business on Linux.

Jan 2015 — Dec 2015

Researcher

«Saint-Petersburg State University», Saint-Petersburg

Research in the field of atomic physics, g factor theory, nuclear recoil effect.

Jan 2014 — Dec 2016

Researcher

«Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics», Moscow

Research in the field of atomic physics supported by "Helmholtz-Rosatom" grant. Theme: "Zeeman splitting in highly-charged ions: novel approach to the non-linear effects".

Sep 2011 — Jan 2012

Teacher (Physics)

«Laboratory for Continuous Mathematical Education», Saint-Petersburg

Teaching physics at 8 and 9 year classes. Special seminars on thermodynamics.

Education

Sep 2013 — Jul 2016 Postgraduate student (Theoretical Physics)

Saint-Petersburg State University

Department of Physics, Division of Quantum Mechanics

Sep 2011 — Jul 2013 **Master's degree** (Quantum Mechanics of Atoms, Molecules and Solids)

Saint-Petersburg State University

Department of Physics, Division of Quantum Mechanics

Sep 2007 — **Bachelor's degree** (Quantum Mechanics of Atoms, Molecules and Solids)

Saint-Petersburg State University
Department of Physics, Division of Quantum Mechanics

Certificates

Coursera Natural Language Processing Specialization

August 2022 D4F2WRLEHCY8

Coursera Natural Language Processing with Attention Models

August 2022 TT5J2NHDYDY2

Coursera Natural Language Processing with Classification and Vector

August 2022 Spaces

3LL65SQH6EWM

Coursera Natural Language Processing with Probabilistic Models

August 2022 C3RSRG7T853E

Coursera Natural Language Processing with Sequence Models

August 2022 667D47FVSK3M

Coursera Combinatorics and Probability

July 2022 EFYQQQ9GUTUP

Coursera Sample-based Learning Methods

June 2022 KC4T942AATVE

Coursera Fundamentals of Reinforcement Learning

May 2022 U3NT5V7XZCNK

Publications

- A. A. Shchepetnov, D. A. Glazov, A. V. Volotka, V. M. Shabaev, I. I. Tupitsyn, G. Plunien "Nuclear recoil correction to the g factor of boron-like argon". Journal of Physics: Conference Series, 2015. — Vol. 583, — P. 012001
- I. A. Aleksandrov, A. A. Shchepetnov, D. A. Glazov, V. M. Shabaev "Finite nuclear size corrections to the recoil effect in hydrogenlike ions". Journal of Physics B: Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics, 2015. — Vol. 48, — No. 14. — P. 144004
- D. A. Glazov, A. V. Volotka, A. A. Schepetnov, M. M. Sokolov, V. M. Shabaev, I. I. Tupitsyn, G. Plunien "g factor of boron-like ions: ground and excited states". Physica Scripta, 2013. — Vol. T156, — P. 014014

International conferences

- Seminar on Astrophysics, Clocks and Fundamental Constants, Bad Honnef, Germany (Poster), 2015
- Topical Workshop of the SPARC Collaboration, Worms, Germany (Poster), 2014
- International Conference on Science and Technology for FAIR, Worms, Germany (Poster), 2014
- International Conference on the Physics of Highly Charged Ions, San Carlos de Bariloche, Argentina (Oral presentation), 2014
- Fin Q workshop: International conference «Quantum Informatics and Applications», St. Petersburg, Russia (No report), 2013
- The Workshop on Precision Physics and Fundamental Physical Constants, Pulkovo, St. Petersburg, Russia (Poster), 2013
- XX Conference on Fundamental Atomic Spectroscopy, Voronezh, Russia (Oral presentation), 2013

Arseniy Shchepetnov